議員想發言。
Australia。
Apology Bill.
立法會主席。
Morning, Mr. President.
但， spending。
啊啊！正係噉樣。
因為我沒有 engage。
要 enact that into law.
我 must confess that I know very little about this.
我哋繼續處理盜竊條例草案，有冇？
It confused me a little. In fact, more than a little.
在研究這特別法案作為法案委員會成員。
當他們講關於這個道歉法案，which is common in Canada。
We are talking about the apology bill that we are about to.
我聽著我的同事的講話和智慧，我必須 confess that。
就。
That.
England.
It is.
The Western.
and UK。
different from。
而，
There's a form of
countries that when they say something they don't mean it.
爭議解決，那 prevent litigation。
somehow misleading because the reason is.
當我們説 sorry，我們應該 remorseful of 什麼？我們 said。
Apologies could be made, but without legal liability.
在我們中華文化，即使我們小，我們被教。
from going through the court, saving courts' time and money, to arrive at a settlement.
係。
this is。
try to。
when I was trying to
and Chinese and an Asian.
Acknowledgement of guilt, without acknowledgement.
當某人 tell 某人，那，
道德經，and says that you do not see。
to say apologies without the meaning of apology.
to to get some understanding. Then I I was reading a piece of.
of wrongdoing， without any meaning of that feeling， just to seek a settlement。
但 now we are passing a law which asks us to have different meaning of sorry, apologies, acknowledgement.
this is something very different to our culture. Just because they practice in states which people are different to us.
但係，way is there？That's the invisible way. That I can understand is a philosophy, or it could be a religion. That the good will be rewarded, the bad will be punished.
saying sorry without the meaning, without the feeling of remorseness, saying sorry without the feeling, without the meaning of sorrow, or even saying sorry without the feeling of sympathy.
And all this is so different to our culture, to our society's belief. What are we teaching our children? I have been a legislator quite for about 18 years. When we pass laws, is the laws must be clear without without any ambiguity.
An apology.
有冇其他嘢想發言？
apologies，sorry，mean。
That, Mr. President, I'm not going to vote on this bill.
如果冇嘅，我現在就請律師、政師、師長答辯，之後辯論即告結束，師長。
所以，Mr. President，我 find it very difficult to be part of。
I'm sorry, I'm wrong, but I do not have any responsibility. This is something that cannot be accepted.
Needless to say, I'm also grateful to the deputations and individuals for the constructive views they put forward in relation to the bill.
我將會在委員會階段提出修正案。在較後的階段，The CSAs，which have all been endorsed by the Bills Committee，can be outlined as follows.
2015和2016，We also provided briefings to the panel on administration of justice and legal services in 2015 and 2016.
this council to enact a law that have so many ambiguous meaning and so have so many hidden hidden understanding of what the words.
提供 unfailing support to the Bills Committee for working within a tight timetable, and thus make it possible to resume the second reading of the bill within this legislative session.
主席，first of all, I would like to express our gratitude to the honourable Holden Chow, the chairman of the Bills Committee of the Apology Bill, the bill, and all the members of the Bills Committee for their contribution in respect of the scrutiny of the bill. In this regard, I would also like to thank the staff of the Legislative Council, who
As I pointed out when I introduced the bill into this council in February this year, the objective of the bill is to facilitate the resolution of disputes by promoting and encouraging the making of apologies by parties in disputes when they want to do so, by stating the legal consequence of making.
是。
with their substantive rights.
with the matter to the prejudice of the person.
決策者是 satisfy that it is just and equitable to do so, having regard to all relevant circumstances.
The CSA in question is also in response to the views of some members on the need for clearer guidelines for the exercise of the disbursements.
An example of such an exceptional case is given in Clause 8, bracket 2, which is where there is no other evidence available for determining an issue.
我們理解那些由成員表達的願望。事實上，這些議題已由司法部深入研究，並由法案委員會廣泛討論。
如果我們要移除這些權限，完全，有個真實的風險，即係呢條條例可能會變成違憲，甚至會引致各種的不確定性。
We take the view that the above proposal will strike an appropriate balance between achieving the policy objective of the bill on the one hand, and safeguarding the interests of the potential claimants on the other.
having consider having carefully considered the views expressed by the members of the Bills Committee and without unduly restricting the discretion of the decision maker, as defined in the Bill, we decided to propose CSA to Clause H bracket two.
such disputes include disputes arising from medical negligence and healthcare cases mentioned by a member at yesterday's debate. The bill was formulated on the basis of the recommendations made by the steering committee on mediation after two rounds of public consultation held in 2015.
條四， of the bill defines an apology as an expression of a person's regret, sympathy or benevolence. If part of that expression is an admission of the person's fault or liability, or a statement of fact, the admission or statement is also included in the meaning of apology.
Under clause H bracket one of the bill, evidence of an apology, including an accompanying statement of fact made by a person in connection with a matter, is not admissible in applicable proceedings as evidence for determining fault, liability or any other issue in connection.
Nevertheless, under the original proposed clause H bracket 2 of the bill, the decision maker of relevant applicable proceedings may exercise a discretion to admit a statement of fact contained in an apology as evidence in relevant proceedings if there is an exceptional case and the.
Some members consider that the discretion of the decision maker, and in particular the words "or developing circumstances" in clause H bracket two, will give rise to uncertainties. Some members took the view that this might deter people from disclosing statements of fact when making a policy.
The effect of the CSA is that if there is an exceptional case in developing particular proceedings, the decision maker has to give regard to the public interest or the interest of the administrations of justice in deciding whether it is just and equitable to exercise the discretion.
We share the views of some members of the Bills Committee that a decision maker would necessarily take into account and consider all relevant circumstances in deciding whether it is just and equitable to exercise discretion, having regard to the public interests and the interests of the administration of justice.
如果佢開始，
reduce hostile litigation.
反對，要從議員要求記名點票，點會爭響五分鐘？
現在嘅代決議題係道歉條例草案予以移動，贊成嘅請舉手。
可適用程序，定義在第6條的法案，以及誰有管轄權決定證據問題。
With these remarks, I urge members to support the passage of the second reading of the bill and the amendments that I will move at the subsequent committee stage. Thank you, President.
為避免任何不必要的 doubt，我們決定提出CSA，以明確地適用道歉法案至立法會的程序，包括其委員會、小組或分組的程序。
as to whether the bill would apply to the proceedings of the legislative council, having regard to the constitutional role and functions of the legislative council, we do not intend to apply the bill to the proceedings of the legislative council.
Any inconsistency, the Chinese expression, and I quote, 公正、公平, end of quote, which can be found in the Chinese version of the bill, has been used as the Chinese equivalent of just and equitable in many of the local legislation.
This, we believe, will help further enhance the Hong Kong SAR's position as a centre for international legal and dispute resolution services in the Asia-Pacific region, and hopefully will also bring about a change in dispute resolution culture.
While the objective of the bill is to encourage the making of sincere and meaningful apologies that include statements of fact, this should not be achieved at the expense of the party's fundamental right to a fair hearing and to secure a just resolution of disputes in a.
在course of yesterday's debate， I noticed that Dr. Honorable You Chengyin suggested that there is an inconsistency between the English version and the Chinese version of Clause (H) bracket two regarding the use of the expression just and equitable. We have looked at the position and do not think that there is.
我 also note that honourable Claudia Mo expressed concern about the position of the decision maker. As defined in clause H bracket four of the bill, the expression decision maker is defined to mean the person, whether a court, a tribunal, an arbitrator.
或任何其他體或個別，具有權力聽、收和審查證據的程序。因此，「決定者」並非指任何一個人，而是指決定者是擁有決定行為的。
Clause six, bracket one, sets out the proceedings to which the bill is applicable. Clause six, bracket two, provides that applicable proceedings do not include criminal proceedings or proceedings specified in the schedule to the bill. When the bill was being considered, a question was raised.
The bill is the latest initiative for implementing the government's policy to encourage the wider use of mediation in resolving disputes. Experiences and studies in other jurisdictions demonstrate that apology legislation would facilitate settlement of disputes and would thereby.
If and when enacted, the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region will be the first jurisdiction in Asia to have apology legislation, and the first jurisdiction amongst the 56 common law jurisdictions that we have studied to protect statements of fact in an apology legislation.
整核對所在咧。
表決，如果冇問題嘅，再停止表決，顯示結果。
盜竊條例草案，會唔會現在成為全體委員會就條例草案嘅辯論同埋？
出席卅五位，贊成卅三位，係一位反對嘅議題係獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。